Introduction

This demonstration ePub 3 book was created with IGP:Digital Publisher for AZARDI. It demonstrates the multi-language power of standards-based digital content production and delivery solutions.

It contains 28 languages listed in an "around the world" sequence. This includes latin character, logographic, scripted and right-to-left representations of many of the worlds languages.

It starts from the Interational Dateline with Maori from New Zealand. The sequence follows the sun around the world with languages ordered approximately by longitude. This was to avoid a default latin alphabetic listing. It was also more fun!

There was considerable language-font-angst with the release of ePub2 and the very limited language options available in most readers and devices. The status of fonts and embedding was ambiguous, and publishers of languages other than English had a difficult time.

At the dawn of ePub 3 it is important that language accessibility is a high priority for most of the world. This ePub 3 attempts to address the issue of language diversity and can be used for testing by anyone.

In 2011 most desktops have all language fonts installed by default, but we have been careful with this first multi-language test book. It needs to work. This ePub 3 contains the Open Source SIL licensed DejaVu font set to ensure that the largest possible set of languages is displayed correctly. To really test other ePub 3 devices and readers a version without font embedding may be released.

Unfortunately the fonts embedded in this book does not include logographic languages such as Chinese, Korean and Japanese, nor the Indic scripted languages. We have to reasonably assume that content users in those languages have the correct fonts installed on their machine. In our own installations modern operating systems make the widest range of fonts available.

As there is currently no reasonable Chinese or Indic fonts available in Open Source with clear SIL (or similar) licenses (that we could find) we have not embedded any of these fonts. We would welcome any information on this.

United Nations Declaration of Universal Rights

This demonstration contains the United Nations Declaration of Universal Rights in 28 different languages in a single ePub 3.

The United Nations Declaration of Universal Rights apparently holds the Guiness Book of Records most translated document record, if that is significant. However it is a very useful for testing digital content and ePub Readers in particular.

Unicode Consortium

What is most important is Unicode and the Unicode Consortium. The content was sourced from the Unicode Consortium.UDHR Project.

All copyright statements have been left intact on each page. Styles and metadata have been added by Infogrid Pacific.

The Unicode Consortium has been working since 1993 to make content accessible to all, in every language. They are perhaps the greatest unsung heros of the computer age. Their achievement transcends operating systems, devices and technology, and addresses the needs of humanity in a unique way.

DejaVu Font Language Coverage

Of the languages included in this ePub 3, the following languages are supported by the included DejaVu Fonts:

Maori
Tagalog
Vietnamese
Thai
Russian
Arabic
Swahili
Amharic
Hebrew
Polish
Greek
German
Italian
French
Spanish
Yoruba
English
Portuguese
Samoan

The languages that AZARDI does not directly support with fonts and where suitable fonts will have to be available from the Operating System:

Japanese
Korean
Chinese
Thai
Tamil
Hindi
Marathi
Panjabi

PANDAIGDIG NA PAGPAPAHAYAG NG MGA KARAPATAN NG TAO

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - Tagalog

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

Noong Disyembre 10, 1948, ang Pangkalahatang Kapulungan ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa ay nagsagawa at nagpahayag ng Pandaigdig na Pahayag ng mga Karapatan ng Tao. Ang buong nilalaman noon ay mababasa sa mga susunod na pahina. Kasunod ng makasaysayang gawaing ito, ang Kapulungan ay nanawagan sa lahat ng mga kagawad ng bansa upang ilathala ang nilalaman ng Pahayag at "upang ito'y palaganapin, itanghal, basahin, at talakayin lalung-lalo na sa mga paaralan at iba pang institusyong edukasyonal, nang walang pagtatangi batay sa kalagayang pulitikal ng mga bansa o mga teritoryo." Pangwakas na Textong May Pahintulot na salin sa Pilipino ng Katipunan ng Bagong Pilipina. Ipinaabot ng Punong Pangkaalaman ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa para sa Pilipinas ang taus-pusong pasasalamat sa Law Center ng Pamantasan ng Pilipinas na unang naglimbag ng pahayag na ito na salin sa Pilipino. Ipinalimbag ng Punong Pangkaalaman ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa para sa Pilipinas at ng Kagawaran ng Kabatirang Pangmadla ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa.

PANIMULA

Sapagkat ang pagkilala sa katutubong karangalan at sa pantay at di-maikakait na mga karapatan ng lahat ng nabibilang sa angkan ng tao ay siyang saligan ng kalayaan, katarungan at kapayapaan sa daigdig.

Sapagkat ang pagwawalang-bahala at paglalapastangan sa mga karapatan ng tao ay nagbunga ng mga gawang di-makatao na humamak sa budhi ng sangkatauhan, at ang pagdatal ng isang daigdig na ang mga tao ay magtatamasa ng kalayaan sa pagsasalita at ng kaligtasan sa pangamba at pagdaralita ay ipinahayag na pinakamataas na mithiin ng mga karaniwang tao.

Sapagkat mahalaga, kung ang tao ay di-pipiliting manghawakan bilang huling magagawa, sa paghihimagsik laban sa paniniil at pang-aapi, na ang mga karapatan ng tao'y mapangalagaan sa pamamagitan ng paghahari ng batas.

Sapagkat mahalagang itaguyod ang pagpapaunlad ng mabuting pagsasamahan ng mga bansa.

Sapagkat ang mga mamamayan ng Mga Bansang Nagkakaisa ay nagpatibay sa Karta ng kanilang pananalig sa mga Saligang karapatan ng tao, sa karangalan at kahalagahan ng pagkatao at sa pantay na mga karapatan ng mga lalaki at babae at nagpapasiyang itaguyod ang kaunlarang panlipunan at lalong mabubuting pamantayan ng buhay sa lalong malaking kalayaan.

Sapagkat ang mga Kasaping Estado ay nangako sa kanilang sarili na tamuhin sa pakikipagtulungan sa mga Bansang Nagkakaisa, ang pagtataguyod ng pandaigdig na paggalang at pagtalima sa mga karapatan ng tao at mga saligang kalayaan.

Sapagkat lubhang mahalaga ang pagkakaunawa ng lahat sa mga karapatan at kalayaang ito at lubhang mahalaga sa ganap na pagsasakatuparan ng mga pangakong ito.

Ngayon, Samakatuwid,

Ang Pangkalahatang Kapulungan

ay nagpapahayag ng

Pandaigdig na Pagpapahayag na ito

ng mga Karapatan ng Tao

bilang pangkalahatang pamantayang maisasagawa para sa lahat ng tao at bansa, sa layuning ang bawat tao at bawat galamay ng lipunan, na laging nasa isip ang Pahayag na ito, ay magsikap sa pamamagitan ng pagtuturo at edukasyon na maitaguyod ang paggalang sa mga karapatan at kalayaang ito at sa pamamagitan ng mga hakbang na pagsulong na pambansa at pandaigdig, ay makamtan ang pangkalahatan at mabisang pagkilala at pagtalima sa mga ito, maging ng mga mamamayan ng mga Kasaping Estado at ng mga mamamayan ng mga teritoryo na nasa ilalim ng kanilang nasasakupan.

Artikulo 1

Ang lahat ng tao'y isinilang na malaya at pantay-pantay sa karangalan at mga karapatan. Sila'y pinagkalooban ng katwiran at budhi at dapat magpalagayan ang isa't isa sa diwa ng pagkakapatiran.

Artikulo 2

Ang bawat tao'y karapat-dapat sa lahat ng karapatan at kalayaang nakalahad sa Pahayag na ito, nang walang ano mang uri ng pagtatangi, gaya ng lahi, kulay, kasarian, wika, relihiyon, kuro-kurong pampulitika o iba pa, pinagmulang bansa o lipunan, ari-arian, kapanganakan o iba pang katayuan.

Bukod dito, walang pagtatanging gagawin batay sa katayuang pampulitika, hurisdiksiyunal o pandaigdig na kalagayan ng bansa o teritoryong kinabibilangan ng isang tao, maging ito ay nagsasarili, itinitiwala, di-nakapamamahala sa sarili o nasa ilalim ng ano mang katakdaan ng soberanya.

Artikulo 3

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa buhay, kalayaan at kapanatagan ng sarili.

Artikulo 4

Walang sino mang aalipinin o bubusabusin; ipagbabawal ang ano mang anyo ng pang-aalipin at ang pangangalakal ng alipin.

Artikulo 5

Walang sino mang pahihirapan o lalapatan ng malupit,di-makatao o nakalalait na pakikitungo sa parusa.

Artikulo 6

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang kilalanin saan mang dako bilang isang tao sa harap ng batas.

Artikulo 7

Ang lahat ay pantay-pantay sa harap ng batas at may karapatan sa walang pagtatangi ng pangangalaga ng batas. Ang lahat ay may karapatan sa pantay na pangangalaga laban sa ano mang pagtatangi-tanging nalalabag sa Pahayag na ito at laban sa ano mang pagbubuyo sa gayong pagtatangi-tangi.

Artikulo 8

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa mabisang lunas ng karampatang mga hukumang pambansa tungkol sa mga gawang lumalabag sa pangunahing mga karapatan na ipinagkaloob sa kanya ng saligang batas o ng batas.

Artikulo 9

Walang sino mang ipaiilalim sa di-makatwirang pagdakip, pagpigil o pagpapatapon.

Artikulo 10

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa ganap na pagkakapantay-pantay, sa isang makatarungan at hayag na paglilitis ng isang hukumang malaya at walang kinikilingan, sa pagpapasiya ng kanyang mga karapatan at panangutan at sa ano mang paratang na kriminal laban sa kanya.

Artikulo 11

1. Ang bawat taong pinararatangan ng pagkakasalang pinarurusahan ay may karapatang ituring na walang-sala hanggang di-napatutunayang nagkasala alinsunod sa batas sa isang hayag na paglilitis na ipinagkaroon niya ng lahat ng garantiyang kailangan sa kanyang pagtatanggol.

2. Walang taong ituturing na nagkasala ng pagkakasalang pinarurusahan dahil sa ano mang gawa o pagkukulang na hindi isang pagkakasalang pinarurusahan, sa ilalim ng batas pambansa o pandaigdig, noong panahong ginawa iyon. Hindi rin ipapataw ang parusang lalong mabigat kaysa nararapat nang panahong magawa ang pagkakasalang pinarurusahan.

Artikulo 12

Walang taong isasailalim sa di-makatwirang panghihimasok sa kanyang pananhimik, pamilya, tahanan o pakikipagsulatang ni sa tuligsa sa kanyang karangalan at mabuting pangalan. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa pangangalaga ng batas laban sa gayong mga panghihimasok o tuligsa.

Artikulo 13

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kalayaan ng pagkilos at paninirahan sa loob ng mga hanggahan ng bawat estado.

2. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang umalis sa alin mang bansa, pati na sa kanyang sarili, at bumalik sa kanyang bansa.

Artikulo 14

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang humanap at magtamasa sa ibang bansa ng pagpapakupkop laban sa pag-uusig.

2. Ang karapatang ito'y hindi mahihingi sa mga pag-uusig na tunay na nagbubuhat sa mga pagkakasalang di-pampulitika o sa mga gawang nasasalungat sa mga layunin at simulain ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa.

Artikulo 15

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa isang pagkamamamayan.

2. Walang sino mang aalisan ng kanyang pagkamamamayan ng walang katwiran ni pagkakaitan ng karapatang magpalit ng kanyang pagkamamamayan.

Artikulo 16

1. Ang mga lalaki't babaeng may sapat na gulang ay may karapatang mag-asawa at magpamilya nang walang ano mang pagtatakda dahil sa lahi, bansang kinabibilangan o relihiyon. Nararapat sila sa pantay-pantay na karapatan sa pag-aasawa, sa panahong may asawa at pagpapawalang bisa nito.

2. Ang pag-aasawa'y papasukan lamang sa pamamagitan ng malaya at lubos na pagsang-ayon ng mga nagbabalak magkapangasawahan.

3. Ang pamilya ay likas at pangunahing pangkat sa sangay ng lipunan at karapat-dapat sa pangangalaga ng lipunan at ng Estado.

Artikulo 17

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang mag-angkin ng ari-arian nang mag-isa gayon din na kasama ng iba.

2. Walang sino mang aalisan ng kanyang ari-arian nang walang katwiran.

Artikulo 18

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kalayaan ng pag-iisip, budhi at relihiyon; kasama sa karapatang ito ang kalayaang magpalit ng kanyang relihiyon o paniniwala maging nag-iisa o kasama ang iba sa pamayanan upang ipakilala ang kanyang relihiyon o paniniwala sa pagtuturo, pagsasagawa,pagsamba at pagtalima.

Artikulo 19

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kalayaan ng pagkukuro at pagpapahayag; kasama ng karapatang ito ang kalayaan at kuru-kuro nang walang panghihimasok at humanap, tumanggap at magbigay ng impormasyon at kaisipan sa pamamagitan ng alin mang paraan ng pagkakalat at walang pagsasaalang-alang ng mga hanggahan.

Artikulo 20

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kalayaan sa mapayapang pagpupulong at pagsasamahan.

2. Walang sino mang pipiliting sumapi sa isang kapisanan.

Artikulo 21

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang makilahok sa pamahalaan ng kanyang bansa, sa tuwiran o sa pamamagitan ng mga kinatawang malayang pinili.

2. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa pantay na pagpasok sa paglilingkod pambayan ng kanyang bansa.

3. Ang kalooban ng bayan ang magiging saligan ng kapangyarihan ng pamahalaan; ang kaloobang ito'y ipahahayag sa tunay na mga halalan sa pana-panahon sa pamamagitan ng pangkalahatan at pantay-pantay na paghahalal at idaraos sa pamamagitan ng lihim na balota o sa katumbas na pamamaraan ng malayang pagboto.

Artikulo 22

Ang bawat tao, bilang kasapi ng lipunan, ay may karapatan sa kapanatagang panlipunan at nararapat na makinabang sa pamamagitan ng pambansang pagsisikap at pakikipagtulungang pandaigdig at alinsunod sa pagkakabuo at mga mapagkukunan ng bawat Estado, sa mga karapatang pangkabuhayan, panlipunan at pangkalinangan na lubhang kailangan para sa kanyang karangalan at sa malayang pagpapaunlad ng kanyang pagkatao.

Artikulo 23

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa paggawa, sa malayang pagpili ng mapapasukang hanapbuhay, sa makatarungan at kanais-nais na mga kalagayan sa paggawa at sa pangangalaga laban sa kawalang mapapasukang hanap-buhay.

2. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kapantay na bayad ng kapantay na gawain, nang walang ano mang pagtatangi.

3. Ang bawat taong gumagawa ay may karapatan sa makatarungan at nababatay sa kabayarang tumitiyak sa kanyang sarili at sa kanyang pamilya ng kabuhayang karapat-dapat sa karangalan ng isang tao, at pupunan, kung kailangan, ng iba pang paraan ng pangangalangang panlipunan.

4. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang magtatag at umanib sa mga unyon ng manggagawa para sa pangangalaga ng kanyang mga kapakanan.

Artikulo 24

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa pamamahinga at paglilibang, kasama ang mga makatwirang pagtatakda ng mga oras ng paggawa at may sahod sa mga pana-panahong pista opisyal.

Artikulo 25

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa isang pamantayan ng pamumuhay na sapat para sa kalusugan at kagalingan ng kanyang sarili at ng kanyang pamilya, kasama na ang pagkain, pananamit, paninirahan at pagpapagamot at kinakailangang mga paglilingkod panlipunan, at ng karapatan sa kapanatagan sa panahong walang gawain, pagkakasakit, pagkabalda, pagkabalo, katandaan at iba pang kakapusan sa ikabubuhay sa mga di-maiiwasang pangyayari.

2. Ang pagkaina at pagkabata ay nararapat sa tanging kalinga at tulong. Ang lahat ng bata, maging anak na lehitimo o di-lehitimo, ay magtatamasa ng gayon ding pangangalagang panlipunan.

Artikulo 26

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa edukasyon. Ang edukasyon ay walang bayad, doon man lamang sa elementarya at pangunahing antas. Ang edukasyong elementarya ay magiging sapilitan. Ang edukasyong teknikal at propesyonal ay gagawing maabot ng lahat at ang lalong mataas na edukasyon ay ipagkakaloob nang pantay-pantay sa lahat batay sa pagiging karapat-dapat.

2. Ang edukasyon ay itutungo sa ganap na pagpapaunlad ng pagkatao at sa pagpapalakas ng paggalang sa mga karapatan ng tao at mga pangunahing kalayaan. Itataguyod nito ang pagkakaunawaan, pagbibigayan, at pagkakaibigan ng lahat ng bansa, mga pangkat na panlahi o panrelihiyon, at palawakin ang mga gawain ng mga Bansang Nagkakaisa sa ikapapanatili ng kapayapaan.

3. Ang mga magulang ay may pangunahing karapatang pumili ng uri ng edukasyong ipagkaloob sa kanilang mga anak.

Artikulo 27

1. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatang makilahok nang malaya sa buhay pangkalinangan ng pamayanan, upang tamasahin ang mga sining at makihati sa mga kaunlaran sa siyensiya at sa mga pakinabang dito.

2. Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa pangangalaga ng mga kapakanang moral at materyal bunga ng alin mang produksiyong pang-agham, pampanitikan o pansining na siya ang may-akda.

Artikulo 28

Ang bawat tao'y may karapatan sa kaayusang panlipunan at pandaigdig na ang mga karapatan at mga kalayaang itinakda sa Pahayag na ito ay ganap na maisasakatuparan.

Artikulo 29

1. Ang bawat tao'y may mga tungkulin sa pamayanan sa ikaaari lamang ng malaya at ganap na pagkaunlad ng kanyang pagkatao.

2. Sa paggamit ng kanyang mga karapatan at mga kalayaan, ang bawat tao'y masasaklaw lamang ng mga katakdaan gaya ng ipinapasya ng batas ng tanging sa layunin lamang ng pagtatamo ng kaukulang pagkilala at paggalang sa mga karapatan at mga kalayaan ng iba at sa pagtugon sa makatarungang kahilingan ng moralidad, kaayusang pambayan at ng pangkalahatang kagalingan sa isang demokratikong lipunan.

3. Ang mga karapatan at kalayaang ito ay hindi magagamit sa ano mang pangyayari nang nasasalungat sa mga layunin at mga simulain ng Mga Bansang Nagkakaisa.

Artikulo 30

Walang bagay sa Pahayag na ito na mapapakahulugan ang nagbibigay sa alin mang Estado, pangkat o tao ng ano mang karapatang gumawa ng ano mang kilusan o magsagawa ng ano mang hakbang na naglalayong sirain ang nakalahad dito.

הכרזה לכל באי עולם בדבר זכויות האדם

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - Hebrew

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

הואיל והכרה בכבוד הטבעי אשר לכל בני משפהת האדם ובזכויותיהם השוות והבלתי נפקעות הוא יסוד החופש, הצדק והשלום בעולם.

הואיל והזלזול בזכויות האדם וביזוין הבשילו מעשים פראיים שפגעו קשה במצפונה של האנושות; ובנין עולם, שבו ייהנו כל יצורי אנוש מחירות הדיבור והאמונה ומן החירות מפחד וממחסור, הוכרז כראש שאיפותיו של כל אדם.

הואיל והכרח חיוני הוא שזכויות האדם תהיינה מוגנות בכוח שלטונו של החוק, שלא יהא האדם אנוס, כמפלט אחרון, להשליך את יהבו על מרידה בעריצות ובדיכזי.

הואיל והכרח חיוני הוא לקדם את התפתחותם של יחסי ידידות בין האומות.

הואיל והעמים המאוגדים בארגון האומות המאוחדות חזרו ואישרו במגילה את אמונתם בזכויות היסוד של האדם, בכבודה ובערכה של אישיותו ובזכות שווה לגבר ולאשה; ומנוי וגמור אתם לסייע לקדמה חברתית ולהעלאת רמת החיים בתוך יתר חירות.

הואיל והמדינות החברות התחייבו לפעול, בשיתוף עם ארגון האומות המאוחדות, לטיפול יחס כבוד כללי אל זכויות האדם ואל חירויות היסוד והקפדה על קיומן.

הואיל והבנה משותפת במהותן של זכויות וחירויות אלה הוא תנאי חשוב לקיומה השלם של התחייבות זו.

לפיכך מכריזש העצרת באזני כל באי העולם את ההכרזש הזאת בדבר זכויות האדם כרמת הישגים כללית לכל העמים והאומות, כדי שכל יחיד וכל גוף חברתי ישווה תמיד לנגד עיניו וישאף לטפח, דרך לימוד וחינוך, יחס של כבוד אל הזכויות ואל החירויות הללו, ולהבטיח באמצעים הדרגתיים, לאומיים ובינלאומיים, שההכרה בעקרונות אלה וההקפדה עליהם תהא כללית ויעילה בקרב אוכלוסי המדינות החברות ובקרב האוכלוסים שבארצות שיפוטם.

סעיף א.

כל בני אדם נולדו בני חורין ושווים בערכם ובזכויותיהם. כולם חוננו בתבונה ובמצפון, לפיכך חובה עליהם לנהוג איש ברעהו ברוח של אחוה.

סעיף ב.

כל אדם זכאי לזכויות ולחרויות שנקבעו בהכרזש זו ללא הפליה כלשהיא מטעמי גזע, צבע, מין, לשון, דח, דעה פוליטית או דעה בבעיות אחרות, בגלל מוצא לאומי או חברתי, קנין, לידה או מעמד אחר.

גדולה מזו, לא יופלה אדם על פי מעמדה המדיני, על פי סמכותה או על פי מעמדה הבינלאומי של המדינה או הארץ שאליה הוא שייך, דין שהארץ היא עצמאית, ובין שהיא נתונה לנאמנות, בין שהיא נטולת שלטון עצמי ובין שריבונותה מוגבלת כל הגבלה אחרת.

סעיף ג.

כל אדם יש לו הזכות לחיים, לחרות ולבטחון אישי.

סעיף ד.

לא יהיה אדם עבד או משועבד; עבדות וסחר עבדים יאסרו לכל צורותיהם.

סעיף ה.

לא יהיה אדם נתון לעינויים, ולא ליחס או לעונש אכזריים, בלתי אנושיים או משפילים.

סעיף ו.

כל אדם זכאי להיות מוכר בכל מקום כאשיות בפני החוק.

סעיף ז.

הכל שווים לפני החוק וזכזאים ללא הפליה להגנה שווה של החוק. הכל זכאים להגנה שווה מפני כל הפליה המפירה את מצוות ההכרזש הזאת ומפני כל הסתה להפליה כזו.

סעיף ח.

כל אחד זכאי לתקנה יעילה מטעם בחי הדין הלאומיים המוסמכים נגד מעשים המפירים את זכויות היסוד שניתנו לו על פי החוקה והחוקים.

סעיף ט.

לא ייאסר אדם, לא ייעצר ולא יוגלה באופן שרירותי.

סעיף י.

כל אדם זכאי, מתוך שויון גמור עם זולתו, למשפט הוגן ופומבי של בית-דין כלתי תלוי וללא משוא פנים בשעה שבאים לקבוע זכויותיו וחובותיו ולברר כל אשמה פלילית שהובאה נגדו.

סעיף יא.

1. אדם שנאשם בעבירה פלילית חזקתו שהוא זכאי, עד שלא הוכחה אשמתו כחוק במשפט פומבי שבי ניתנו לו כל הערובות הדרושות להגנתו.

2. לא יורשע אדם בעבירה פלילית על מעשה או על הזנחה שלא נחשבו בשעתם לעבירה פלילית לפי החוק הלאומי או הבינלאומי. לא יוטל עונש חמור מהעונש שהיה נוהג בזמן שעבר את העבירה הפלילית.

סעיף יב.

לא יהא אדם נתון להתערבות שרירותית בחייו הפרטיים, במשפחתו, במעונו, בחליפת מכתבים שלו ולא לפגיעה בכבודו או בשמו הפוב. כל אדם זכאי להגנת החוק בפני התערבות או פגיעה באלה.

סעיף יג.

1. כל אדם זכאי לחופש תנועה ומגורים בתוך כל מדיוה.

2. כל אדם זכאי לעזוב כל ארץ, לרבות ארצו, ולחזור אל ארצו.

סעיף יד.

1. כל אדם זכאי לבקש ולמצוא בארצות אחרות מקלט מרדיפות.

2. אין להסתמך על זכות זו במקרה של האשמה פלילית שמקורה האמיתי במעשי פשע לא-מדיניים או במעשים שהם בניגוד למטרותיהן ולעקרונותיהן של האומות המאוחדות.

סעיף טו.

1. כל אדם זכאי לאזרחות.

2. לא תישלל מאדם אזרחותו דרך שרירות ולא תקופח דרך שרירות זכותו להחליף את אזרחותו.

סעיף טז.

1. כל איש ואשה שהגיעו לפרקם רשאים לבוא בברית הנשואין ולהקים משפחה, ללא כל הגבלה מטעמי גזע, אזרחות או דת. הם זכאים לזכויות שוות במעשה הנשואין בתקופת הנשואין ובשעת ביפולם.

2. נישואין יערכו רק מתוך הסמה חופשית ומלאה של בני הזוג המיועדים.

3. המשפחה היא היחידה הטבעית והבסיסית של החברה וזכאית להגנה של החברה והמדינה.

סעיף יז.

1. כל אדם זכאי להיות בעל קנין, בין לבדו ובין ביחד עם אחרים.

2. לא יישלל מאדם קנינו דרך שרירות.

סעיף יח.

כל אדם זכאי לחירות המחשבה, המצפון והדת; חירות זו כוללת את הזכות להמיר את דתו או את אמונתו ולתת בטוי לדתו או לאמונתו, לבדו או כציבור, ברשות היחיד או ברשות הרבים, דרך הוראה, נוהג, פולחן ושמירת מצוות.

סעיף יט.

כל אדם זכאי לחירות הדעה והבטוי, לרבות החירות להחיק בדעות ללא כל הפרעה, ולבקש ידיעות ודעות, ולקבלן ולמסרן בכל הדרכים וללא סייגי גבולות.

סעיף ב.

1. כל אדם זכאי לחירות ההתאספות וההתאגדות בדרכי שלום.

2. לא יכפו על אדם השתייכות לאגודה.

סעיף כא.

1. כל אדם זכאי להשתתף בהנהלת ארצו, בין השתתפות ישירה ובין דרך נציגות שובחרה בבחירות חופשיות.

2. כל אדם זכאי לשויון בכניסן בכניסה לשירות במנגנון של ארצו.

3. רצון העם הוא היסוד לסמכותה של הממשלה. העם ידיע את רצונו בבחירות כשרות הנשנות לעיתים מזזמנות, לפי זכות בחירה כללית ושווה ובהצבעה חשאית, או לפי סדר של בחירה חופשית כיוצא בזש.

סעיף כב.

כל אדם, כחבר החברה, זכאי לבטחון סוציאלי וזכאי לתבוע שהזכויות הכלכליות הסוציאליות והתרבותיות, שהן חיוניות לכבודו כאדם ולהתפתחות החופשית של אישיותו, יובטחו במשמץ לאומי ובשיתוף פעולה בינלאומי בהתאם לארגונה ולאוצרותיה של המדינה.

סעיף כג.

1. כל אדם זכאי לעבודה, לבחירה חופשית של עבודתו, לתנאי עבודה צודקים והוגנים ולהגנה מפני אבטלה.

2. כל אדם, ללא כל הפכיה, זכאי לשכר שווה בעד עבודה שווה.

3. כל עובד זכאי לשכר צודק והוגן, אשר יבטיח לו ולבני ביתו קיום הראוי לכבוד האדם שיושלם, אם יהיה צורך בכך, על ידי אמצעים אחרים של הגנה סוציאלית.

4. כל אדם זכאי לאגד אגודות מקצועיות ולהצטרף לאגודות כדי להגן על עניניו.

סעיף כד.

כל אדם זכאי למנוחה ולפנאי, ובכלל זש הגבלת שעות העבודה במידה המתקבלת על הדעת וחופשה בשכר לעיתים מזומנות.

סעיף כה.

1. כל אדם זכאי לרמת חיים נאותה לבריאותם ולרווחתם, שלו ושל בני ביתנ. לרבות מזון, לבוש, שיכון, טיפול רפואי, שירותים סוציאליים כדרוש וזכות לבטחון במקרה של אבטלה, מחלה, אי-כושר לעבודה, אלמון, זקנה או מחסור אחר בנסיבות שאינן תלויות בו.

2. אמהות וילדות זכאיות לטיפול מיוחד ולסיוע. כל הילדים, בין שנולדו בנשואין או שלא בנשואין, יהנו במידה שווה מהגנה סוציאלית.

סעיף כו.

1. כל אדם זכאי לחינוך. החינוך ינתן חינם, לפחות בשלבים הראשונים והיסודיים; החינוך בשלב הראשון הוא חובה. החינוך הטכני והמקצועי יהיה מצוי לכל, והחינוך הגבוה יהיה פתוח לכל במידה שווה שעל יסוד הכשרון.

2. החינוך יכוון לפיתוחה המלא של האישיות ולטיפוח יחס כבוד לזכויות האדם ולחירויות היסודיות; החינוך יטפח הבנה, סובלנות וידידות בין כל העמים והקיבוצים הדתיים והגזעיים, ויסייע למאמץ של האומות המאוחדות לקיים את השלום.

3. להורים זכות בכורה לבחור את דרך החינוך ליליהם.

סעיף כז.

1. אדם זכאי להשתתף תוך חירות בחייו התרבותיים של הציבור, ליהנות מהאמנויות ולהיות שותף בהתקדמות המדע ובברכתו.

2. כל אדם זכאי לוגנת האינטרסים המוסריים והחמריים הכרוכים בכל יצירה מדעית, ספרותית, או אמנותית שהיא פרי רוחו.

סעיף כח.

כל אדם זכאי למשטר סוציאלי ובינלאומי, שבו אפשר יהיה לקיים במלואן את הזכויות והחרויות אשר נקבעו בהכזש זו.

סעיף כט.

1. כל אדם יש לו חובות כלפי הכלל, כי רק בתוך הכלל נתונה לו האפשרות להתפתחות החופשית והמלאה של אישיותו.

2. לא יוגבל אדם בזכויותיו ובחירויותיו, פרט לאותן ההגבלות שנקבעו בחוק על מנת להבטיח את ההכרה בזכויות ובחירויות של הזולת ואת יחס הכבוד אליהן, וכן את מילוי הדרישות הצודקות של המוסר, של הסדר הציבורי ושל טובת הכלל בתוך חברה דמוקרטית.

3. לעולם לא ישתמשו בזכויות ובחירויות אלה בניגוד למטרותיהן ולעקרונותיהן של האומות המאוחדות.

סעיף ל.

שום דבר בהכרזש זו לא יתפרש כאילו הוא בא להקנות למדינה, לציבור או ליחיד כל זכות שהיא לעסוק בפעולה או לבצע מעשה שתכליתם לקפח כל זכות או חירות מן הזכויות והחירויות הקבועות בהכרש זאת.

POWSZECHNA DEKLARACJA PRAW CZŁOWIEKA

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - Polish

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

Trzecia Sesja Ogólnego Zgromadzenia ONZ, obradująca w Paryżu, uchwaliła 10 grudnia 1948 roku jednomyślnie Powszechną Deklarację Praw Człowieka. Dokument ten stanowi niewątpliwie jedno z największych i najtrwalszych osiągnięć ONZ. Przetłumaczona na większość języków świata Powszechna Deklaracja Praw Człowieka zbiera oraz porządkuje osiągnięcia i postulaty człowieka, który od wielu setek lat toczy nie skończoną jeszcze walkę o swoją wolność i swoją godność.

Preambuła

ZWAŻYWSZY, że uznanie przyrodzonej godności oraz równych i niezbywalnych praw wszystkich członków wspólnoty ludzkiej jest podstawą wolności, sprawiedliwości i pokoju świata,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że nieposzanowanie i nieprzestrzeganie praw człowieka doprowadziło do aktów barbarzyństwa, które wstrząsnęły sumieniem ludzkości, i że ogłoszono uroczyście jako najwznioślejszy cel ludzkości dążenie do zbudowania takiego świata, w którym ludzie korzystać będą z wolności słowa i przekonań oraz z wolności od strachu i nędzy,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że konieczne jest zawarowanie praw człowieka przepisami prawa, aby nie musiał - doprowadzony do ostateczności - uciekać się do buntu przeciw tyranii i uciskowi,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że konieczne jest popieranie rozwoju przyjaznych stosunków między narodami,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że Narody Zjednoczone przywróciły swą wiarę w podstawowe prawa człowieka, godność i wartość jednostki oraz w równouprawnienie mężczyzn i kobiet, oraz wyraziły swe zdecydowanie popierania postępu społecznego i poprawy warunków życia w większej wolności,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że Państwa Członkowskie podjęły się we współpracy z Organizacją Narodów Zjednoczonych zapewnić powszechne poszanowanie i przestrzeganie praw człowieka i podstawowych wolności,

ZWAŻYWSZY, że jednakowe rozumienie tych praw i wolności ma olbrzymie znaczenie dla ich pełnej realizacji,

PRZETO ZGROMADZENIE OGÓLNE

Ogłasza Uroczyście niniejszą Powszechną Deklarację Praw Człowieka jako wspólny najwyższy cel wszystkich ludów i wszystkich narodów, aby wszyscy ludzie i wszystkie organy społeczeństwa - mając stale w pamięci niniejszą Deklarację - dążyły w drodze nauczania i wychowywania do rozwijania poszanowania tych praw i wolności i aby zapewniły za pomocą postępowych środków o zasięgu krajowym i międzynarodowym powszechne i skuteczne uznanie i stosowanie tej Deklaracji zarówno wśród narodów Państw Członkowskich, jak i wśród narodów zamieszkujących obszary podległe ich władzy.

Artykuł 1

Wszyscy ludzie rodzą się wolni i równi pod względem swej godności i swych praw. Są oni obdarzeni rozumem i sumieniem i powinni postępować wobec innych w duchu braterstwa.

Artykuł 2

Każdy człowiek posiada wszystkie prawa i wolności zawarte w niniejszej Deklaracji bez względu na jakiekolwiek różnice rasy, koloru, płci, języka, wyznania, poglądów politycznych i innych, narodowości, pochodzenia społecznego, majątku, urodzenia lub jakiegokolwiek innego stanu.

Nie wolno ponadto czynić żadnej różnicy w zależności od sytuacji politycznej, prawnej lub międzynarodowej kraju lub obszaru, do którego dana osoba przynależy, bez względu na to, czy dany kraj lub obszar jest niepodległy, czy też podlega systemowi powiernictwa, nie rządzi się samodzielnie lub jest w jakikolwiek sposób ograniczony w swej niepodległości.

Artykuł 3

Każdy człowiek ma prawo do życia, wolności i bezpieczeństwa swej osoby.

Artykuł 4

Nie wolno nikogo czynić niewolnikiem ani nakładać na nikogo służebności; niewolnictwo i handel niewolnikami są zakazane we wszystkich swych postaciach.

Artykuł 5

Nie wolno nikogo torturować ani karać lub traktować w sposób okrutny, nieludzki lub poniżający.

Artykuł 6

Każdy człowiek ma prawo do uznawania wszędzie jego osobowości prawnej.

Artykuł 7

Wszyscy są równi wobec prawa i mają prawo, bez jakiejkolwiek różnicy, do jednakowej ochrony prawnej. Wszyscy mają prawo do jednakowej ochrony przed jakąkolwiek dyskryminacją, będącą pogwałceniem niniejszej Deklaracji, i przed jakimkolwiek narażeniem na taką dyskryminację.

Artykuł 8

Każdy człowiek ma prawo do skutecznego odwoływania się do kompetentnych sądów krajowych przeciw czynom stanowiącym pogwałcenie podstawowych praw przyznanych mu przez konstytucję lub przez prawo.

Artykuł 9

Nikogo nie wolno samowolnie aresztować, zatrzymać lub wygnać z kraju.

Artykuł 10

Każdy człowiek ma na warunkach całkowitej równości prawo, aby przy rozstrzyganiu o jego prawach i zobowiązaniach lub o zasadności wysuwanego przeciw niemu oskarżenia o popełnienie przestępstwa być słuchanym sprawiedliwie i publicznie przez niezależny i bezstronny sąd.

Artykuł 11

1. Każdy człowiek oskarżony o popełnienie przestępstwa ma prawo, aby uznawano go za niewinnego dopóty, dopóki nie udowodni mu się winy zgodnie z prawem podczas publicznego procesu, w którym zapewniono mu wszystkie konieczne środki obrony.

2. Nikt nie może być skazany za przestępstwo z powodu działania lub zaniechania nie stanowiącego w chwili jego dokonania przestępstwa według prawa krajowego lub międzynarodowego. Nie wolno także wymierzać kary wyższej niż ta, która była przewidziana w chwili popełnienia przestępstwa.

Artykuł 12

Nie wolno ingerować samowolnie w czyjekolwiek życie prywatne, rodzinne, domowe, ani w jego korespondencję, ani też uwłaczać jego honorowi lub dobremu imieniu. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do ochrony prawnej przeciwko takiej ingerencji lub uwłaczaniu.

Artykuł 13

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo swobodnego poruszania się i wyboru miejsca zamieszkania w granicach każdego Państwa.

2. Każdy człowiek ma prawo opuścić jakikolwiek kraj, włączając w to swój własny, i powrócić do swego kraju.

Artykuł 14

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo ubiegać się o azyl i korzystać z niego w innym kraju w razie prześladowania.

2. Nie można powoływać się na to prawo w przypadku ścigania wszczętego rzeczywiście z powodu popełnienia przestępstwa pospolitego lub czynu sprzecznego z celami i zasadami Organizacji Narodów Zjednoczonych.

Artykuł 15

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do posiadania obywatelstwa.

2. Nie wolno nikogo pozbawiać samowolnie obywatelstwa ani nikomu odmawiać prawa do zmiany obywatelstwa.

Artykuł 16

1. Mężczyźni i kobiety bez względu na jakiekolwiek różnice rasy, narodowości lub wyznania mają prawo po osiągnięciu pełnoletności do zawarcia małżeństwa i założenia rodziny. Mają oni równe prawa w odniesieniu do zawierania małżeństwa, podczas jego trwania i po jego ustaniu.

2. Małżeństwo może być zawarte jedynie za swobodnie wyrażoną pełną zgodą przyszłych małżonków.

3. Rodzina jest naturalną i podstawową komórką społeczeństwa i ma prawo do ochrony ze strony społeczeństwa i Państwa.

Artykuł 17

1. Każdy człowiek, zarówno sam jak i wespół z innymi, ma prawo do posiadania własności.

2. Nie wolno nikogo samowolnie pozbawiać jego własności.

Artykuł 18

Każdy człowiek ma prawo wolności myśli, sumienia i wyznania; prawo to obejmuje swobodę zmiany wyznania lub wiary oraz swobodę głoszenia swego wyznania lub wiary bądź indywidualnie, bądź wespół z innymi ludźmi, publicznie i prywatnie, poprzez nauczanie, praktykowanie, uprawianie kultu i przestrzeganie obyczajów.

Artykuł 19

Każdy człowiek ma prawo wolności opinii i wyrażania jej; prawo to obejmuje swobodę posiadania niezależnej opinii, poszukiwania, otrzymywania i rozpowszechniania informacji i poglądów wszelkimi środkami, bez względu na granice.

Artykuł 20

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo spokojnego zgromadzania i stowarzyszania się.

2. Nikogo nie można zmuszać do należenia do jakiegoś stowarzyszenia.

Artykuł 21

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do uczestniczenia w rządzeniu swym krajem bezpośrednio lub poprzez swobodnie wybranych przedstawicieli.

2. Każdy człowiek ma prawo równego dostępu do służby publicznej w swym kraju.

3. Wola ludu jest podstawą władzy rządu; wola ta wyraża się w przeprowadzanych okresowo rzetelnych wyborach, opartych na zasadzie powszechności, równości i tajności, lub na innej równorzędnej procedurze, zapewniającej wolność wyborów.

Artykuł 22

Każdy człowiek ma jako członek społeczeństwa prawo do ubezpieczeń społecznych; ma również prawo do urzeczywistniania - poprzez wysiłek narodowy i współpracę międzynarodową oraz zgodnie z organizacją i zasobami każdego Państwa - swych praw gospodarczych, społecznych i kulturalnych, niezbędnych dla jego godności i swobodnego rozwoju jego osobowości.

Artykuł 23

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do pracy, do swobodnego wyboru pracy, do odpowiednich i zadowalających warunków pracy oraz do ochrony przed bezrobociem.

2. Każdy człowiek, bez względu na jakiekolwiek różnice, ma prawo do równej płacy za równą pracę.

3. Każdy pracujący ma prawo do odpowiedniego i zadowalającego wynagrodzenia, zapewniającego jemu i jego rodzinie egzystencję odpowiadającą godności ludzkiej i uzupełnianego w razie potrzeby innymi środkami pomocy społecznej.

4. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do tworzenia związków zawodowych i do przystępowania do związków zawodowych dla ochrony swych interesów.

Artykuł 24

Każdy człowiek ma prawo do urlopu i wypoczynku, włączając w to rozsądne ograniczenie godzin pracy i okresowe płatne urlopy.

Artykuł 25

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do stopy życiowej zapewniającej zdrowie i dobrobyt jego i jego rodziny, włączając w to wyżywienie, odzież, mieszkanie, opiekę lekarską i konieczne świadczenia socjalne, oraz prawo do ubezpieczenia na wypadek bezrobocia, choroby, niezdolności do pracy, wdowieństwa, starości lub utraty środków do życia w inny sposób od niego niezależny.

2. Matka i dziecko mają prawo do specjalnej opieki i pomocy. Wszystkie dzieci, zarówno małżeńskie jak i pozamałżeńskie, korzystają z jednakowej ochrony społecznej.

Artykuł 26

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do nauki. Nauka jest bezpłatna, przynajmniej na stopniu podstawowym. Nauka podstawowa jest obowiązkowa. Oświata techniczna i zawodowa jest powszechnie dostępna, a studia wyższe są dostępne dla wszystkich na zasadzie równości w zależności od zalet osobistych.

2. Celem nauczania jest pełny rozwój osobowości ludzkiej i ugruntowanie poszanowania praw człowieka i podstawowych wolności. Krzewi ono zrozumienie, tolerancję i przyjaźń między wszystkimi narodami, grupami rasowymi lub religijnymi; popiera działalność Organizacji Narodów Zjednoczonych zmierzającą do utrzymania pokoju.

3. Rodzice mają prawo pierwszeństwa w wyborze nauczania, które ma być dane ich dzieciom.

Artykuł 27

1. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do swobodnego uczestniczenia w życiu kulturalnym społeczeństwa, do korzystania ze sztuki, do uczestniczenia w postępie nauki i korzystania z jego dobrodziejstw.

2. Każdy człowiek ma prawo do ochrony moralnych i materialnych korzyści wynikających z jakiejkolwiek jego działalności naukowej, literackiej lub artystycznej.

Artykuł 28

Każdy człowiek ma prawo do takiego porządku społecznego i międzynarodowego, w którym prawa i wolności zawarte w niniejszej Deklaracji byłyby w pełni realizowane.

Artykuł 29

1. Każdy człowiek ma obowiązki wobec społeczeństwa, bez którego niemożliwy jest swobodny i pełny rozwój jego osobowości.

2. W korzystaniu ze swych praw i wolności każdy człowiek podlega jedynie takim ograniczeniom, które są ustalone przez prawo wyłącznie w celu zapewnienia odpowiedniego uznania i poszanowania praw i wolności innych i w celu uczynienia zadość słusznym wymogom moralności, porządku publicznego i powszechnego dobrobytu demokratycznego społeczeństwa.

3. Z niniejszych praw i wolności nie wolno w żadnym przypadku korzystać w sposób sprzeczny z celami i zasadami Organizacji Narodów Zjednoczonych.

Artykuł 30

Żadnego z postanowień niniejszej Deklaracji nie można rozumieć jako udzielającego jakiemukolwiek Państwu, grupie lub osobie jakiegokolwiek prawa do podejmowania działalności lub wydawania aktów zmierzających do obalenia któregokolwiek z praw i wolności zawartych w niniejszej Deklaracji.

ΟΙΚΟΥΜΕΝΙΚΗ ΔΙΑΚΗΡΥΞΗ ΓΙΑ ΤΑ ΑΝΘΡΩΠΙΝΑ ΔΙΚΑΙΩΜΑΤΑ

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - Greek (monotonic)

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

10 ΔΕΚΕΜΒΡΙΟΥ 1948

ΠΡΟΟΙΜΙΟ

Επειδή η αναγνώριση της αξιοπρέπειας, που είναι σύμφυτη σε όλα τα μέλη της ανθρώπινης οικογένειας, καθώς και των ίσων και αναπαλλοτρίωτων δικαιωμάτων τους αποτελεί το θεμέλιο της ελευθερίας, της δικαιοσύνης και της ειρήνης στον κόσμο.

Επειδή η παραγνώριση και η περιφρόνηση των δικαιωμάτων του ανθρώπου οδήγησαν σε πράξεις βαρβαρότητας, που εξεγείρουν την ανθρώπινη συνείδηση, και η προοπτική ενός κόσμου όπου οι άνθρωποι θα είναι ελεύθεροι να μιλούν και να πιστεύουν, λυτρωμένοι από τον τρόμο και την αθλιότητα, έχει διακηρυχθεί ως η πιο υψηλή επιδίωξη του ανθρώπου.

Επειδή έχει ουσιαστική σημασία να προστατεύονται τα ανθρώπινα δικαιώματα από ένα καθεστώς δικαίου, ώστε ο άνθρωπος να μην αναγκάζεται να προσφεύγει, ως έσχατο καταφύγιο, στην εξέγερση κατά της τυραννίας και της καταπίεσης.

Επειδή έχει ουσιαστική σημασία να ενθαρρύνεται η ανάπτυξη φιλικών σχέσεων ανάμεσα στα έθνη.

Επειδή, με τον καταστατικό Χάρτη, οι λαοί των Ηνωμένων Εθνών διακήρυξαν και πάλι την πίστη τους στα θεμελιακά δικαιώματα του ανθρώπου, στην αξιοπρέπεια και την αξία της ανθρώπινης προσωπικότητας, στην ισότητα δικαιωμάτων ανδρών και γυναικών, και διακήρυξαν πως είναι αποφασισμένοι να συντελέσουν στην κοινωνική πρόοδο και να δημιουργήσουν καλύτερες συνθήκες ζωής στα πλαίσια μιας ευρύτερης ελευθερίας.

Επειδή τα κράτη μέλη ανέλαβαν την υποχρέωση να εξασφαλίσουν, σε συνεργασία με τον Οργανισμό των Ηνωμένων Εθνών, τον αποτελεσματικό σεβασμό των δικαιωμάτων του ανθρώπου και των θεμελιακών ελευθεριών σε όλο τον κόσμο.

Επειδή η ταυτότητα αντιλήψεων ως προς τα δικαιώματα και τις ελευθερίες αυτές έχει εξαιρετική σημασία για να εκπληρωθεί πέρα ως πέρα αυτή η υποχρέωση,

Η ΓΕΝΙΚΗ ΣΥΝΕΛΕΥΣΗ

Διακηρύσσει ότι η παρούσα Οικουμενική Διακήρυξη των Δικαιωμάτων του Ανθρώπου αποτελεί το κοινό ιδανικό στο οποίο πρέπει να κατατείνουν όλοι οι λαοί και όλα τα έθνη, έτσι ώστε κάθε άτομο και κάθε όργανο της κοινωνίας, με τη Διακήρυξη αυτή διαρκώς στη σκέψη, να καταβάλλει, με τη διδασκαλία και την παιδεία, κάθε προσπάθεια για να αναπτυχθεί ο σεβασμός των δικαιωμάτων και των ελευθεριών αυτών, και να εξασφαλιστεί προοδευτικά, με εσωτερικά και διεθνή μέσα, η παγκόσμια και αποτελεσματική εφαρμογή τους, τόσο ανάμεσα στους λαούς των ίδιων των κρατών μελών όσο και ανάμεσα στους πληθυσμούς χωρών που βρίσκονται στη δικαιοδοσία τους.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 1

'Ολοι οι άνθρωποι γεννιούνται ελεύθεροι και ίσοι στην αξιοπρέπεια και τα δικαιώματα. Είναι προικισμένοι με λογική και συνείδηση, και οφείλουν να συμπεριφέρονται μεταξύ τους με πνεύμα αδελφοσύνης.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 2

Κάθε άνθρωπος δικαιούται να επικαλείται όλα τα δικαιώματα και όλες τις ελευθερίες που προκηρύσσει η παρούσα Διακήρυξη, χωρίς καμία απολύτως διάκριση, ειδικότερα ως προς τη φυλή, το χρώμα, το φύλο, τη γλώσσα, τις θρησκείες, τις πολιτικές ή οποιεσδήποτε άλλες πεποιθήσεις, την εθνική ή κοινωνική καταγωγή, την περιουσία, τη γέννηση ή οποιαδήποτε άλλη κατάσταση.

Δεν θα μπορεί ακόμα να γίνεται καμία διάκριση εξαιτίας του πολιτικού, νομικού ή διεθνούς καθεστώτος της χώρας από την οποία προέρχεται κανείς, είτε πρόκειται για χώρα ή εδαφική περιοχή ανεξάρτητη, υπό κηδεμονία ή υπεξουσία, ή που βρίσκεται υπό οποιονδήποτε άλλον περιορισμό κυριαρχίας.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 3

Κάθε άτομο έχει δικαίωμα στη ζωή, την ελευθερία και την προσωπική του ασφάλεια.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 4

Κανείς δεν επιτρέπεται να ζει υπό καθεστώς δουλείας, ολικής ή μερικής. Η δουλεία και το δουλεμπόριο υπό οποιαδήποτε μορφή απαγορεύονται.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 5

Κανείς δεν επιτρέπεται να υποβάλλεται σε βασανιστήρια ούτε σε ποινή ή μεταχείριση σκληρή, απάνθρωπη ή ταπεινωτική.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 6

Καθένας, όπου και αν βρίσκεται, έχει δικαίωμα στην αναγνώριση της νομικής του προσωπικότητας.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 7

'Ολοι είναι ίσοι απέναντι στον νόμο και έχουν δικαίωμα σε ίση προστασία του νόμου, χωρίς καμία απολύτως διάκριση. 'Ολοι έχουν δικαίωμα σε ίση προστασία από κάθε διάκριση που θα παραβίαζε την παρούσα Διακήρυξη και από κάθε πρόκληση για μια τέτοια δυσμενή διάκριση.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 8

Καθένας έχει δικαίωμα να ασκεί αποτελεσματικά ένδικα μέσα στα αρμόδια εθνικά δικαστήρια κατά των πράξεων που παραβιάζουν τα θεμελιακά δικαιώματα τα οποία του αναγνωρίζουν το Σύνταγμα και ο νόμος.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 9

Κανείς δεν μπορεί να συλλαμβάνεται, να κρατείται ή να εξορίζεται αυθαίρετα.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 10

Καθένας έχει δικαίωμα, με πλήρη ισότητα, να εκδικάζεται η υπόθεσή του δίκαια και δημόσια, από δικαστήριο ανεξάρτητο και αμερόληπτο, που θα αποφασίσει είτε για τα δικαιώματα και τις υποχρεώσεις του είτε, σε περίπτωση ποινικής διαδικασίας, για το βάσιμο της κατηγορίας που στρέφεται εναντίον του.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 11

1. Κάθε κατηγορούμενος για ποινικό αδίκημα πρέπει να θεωρείται αθώος, ωσότου διαπιστωθεί η ενοχή του σύμφωνα με τον νόμο, σε ποινική δίκη, κατά την οποία θα του έχουν εξασφαλιστεί όλες οι απαραίτητες για την υπεράσπισή του εγγυήσεις.

2. Κανείς δεν θα καταδικάζεται για πράξεις ή παραλείψεις που, κατά τον χρόνο που τελέστηκαν, δεν συνιστούσαν αξιόποινο αδίκημα κατά το εσωτερικό ή το διεθνές δίκαιο. Επίσης, δεν επιβάλλεται ποινή βαρύτερη από εκείνη που ίσχυε κατά τον χρόνο που τελέστηκε η αξιόποινη πράξη.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 12

Κανείς δεν επιτρέπεται να υποστεί αυθαίρετες επεμβάσεις στην ιδιωτική του ζωή, την οικογένεια, την κατοικία ή την αλληλογραφία του, ούτε προσβολές της τιμής και της υπόληψης του. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να τον προστατεύουν οι νόμοι από επεμβάσεις και προσβολές αυτού του είδους.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 13

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να κυκλοφορεί ελεύθερα και να εκλέγει τον τόπο της διαμονής του στο εσωτερικό ενός κράτους.

2. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να εγκαταλείπει οποιαδήποτε χώρα, ακόμα και τη δική του, και να επιστρέφει σε αυτήν.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 14

1. Κάθε άτομο που καταδιώκεται έχει το δικαίωμα να ζητά άσυλο και του παρέχεται άσυλο σε άλλες χώρες.

2. Το δικαίωμα αυτό δεν μπορεί κανείς να το επικαλεστεί, σε περίπτωση δίωξης για πραγματικό αδίκημα του κοινού ποινικού δικαίου ή για ενέργειες αντίθετες προς τους σκοπούς και τις αρχές του ΟΗΕ.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 15

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα μιας ιθαγένειας.

2. Κανείς δεν μπορεί να στερηθεί αυθαίρετα την ιθαγένειά του ούτε το δικαίωμα να αλλάξει ιθαγένεια.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 16

1. Από τη στιγμή που θα φθάσουν σε ηλικία γάμου, ο άνδρας και η γυναίκα, χωρίς κανένα περιορισμό εξαιτίας της φυλής, της εθνικότητας ή της θρησκείας, έχουν το δικαίωμα να παντρεύονται και να ιδρύουν οικογένεια. Και οι δύο έχουν ίσα δικαιώματα ως προς τον γάμο, κατά τη διάρκεια του γάμου και κατά τη διάλυσή του.

2. Γάμος δεν μπορεί να συναφθεί παρά μόνο με ελεύθερη και πλήρη συναίνεση των μελλονύμφων.

3. Η οικογένεια είναι το φυσικό και το βασικό στοιχείο της κοινωνίας και έχει το δικαίωμα προστασίας από την κοινωνία και το κράτος.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 17

1. Κάθε άτομο, μόνο του ή με άλλους μαζί, έχει το δικαίωμα της ιδιοκτησίας.

2. Κανείς δεν μπορεί να στερηθεί αυθαίρετα την ιδιοκτησία του.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 18

Κάθε άτομο έχει το δικαίωμα της ελευθερίας της σκέψης, της συνείδησης και της θρησκείας. Στο δικαίωμα αυτό περιλαμβάνεται η ελευθερία για την αλλαγή της θρησκείας ή πεποιθήσεων, όπως και η ελευθερία να εκδηλώνει κανείς τη θρησκεία του ή τις θρησκευτικές του πεποιθήσεις, μόνος ή μαζί με άλλους, δημόσια ή ιδιωτικά, με τη διδασκαλία, την άσκηση, τη λατρεία και με την τέλεση θρησκευτικών τελετών.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 19

Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα της ελευθερίας της γνώμης και της έκφρασης, που σημαίνει το δικαίωμα να μην υφίσταται δυσμενείς συνέπειες για τις γνώμες του, και το δικαίωμα να αναζητεί, να παίρνει και να διαδίδει πληροφορίες και ιδέες, με οποιοδήποτε μέσο έκφρασης, και από όλο τον κόσμο.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 20

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να συνέρχεται και να συνεταιρίζεται ελεύθερα και για ειρηνικούς σκοπούς.

2. Κανείς δεν μπορεί να υποχρεωθεί να συμμετέχει σε ορισμένο σωματείο.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 21

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να συμμετέχει στη διακυβέρνηση της χώρας του, άμεσα ή έμμεσα, με αντιπροσώπους ελεύθερα εκλεγμένους.

2. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να γίνεται δεκτός, υπό ίσους όρους, στις δημόσιες υπηρεσίες της χώρας του.

3. Η λαϊκή θέληση είναι το θεμέλιο της κρατικής εξουσίας. Η θέληση αυτή πρέπει να εκφράζεται με τίμιες εκλογές, οι οποίες πρέπει να διεξάγονται περιοδικά, με καθολική, ίση και μυστική ψηφοφορία, ή με αντίστοιχη διαδικασία που να εξασφαλίζει την ελευθερία της εκλογής.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 22

Κάθε άτομο, ως μέλος του κοινωνικού συνόλου, έχει δικαίωμα κοινωνικής προστασίας. Η κοινωνία, με την εθνική πρωτοβουλία και τη διεθνή συνεργασία, ανάλογα πάντα με την οργάνωση και τις οικονομικές δυνατότητες κάθε κράτους, έχει χρέος να του εξασφαλίσει την ικανοποίηση των οικονομικών, κοινωνικών και πολιτιστικών δικαιωμάτων που είναι απαραίτητα για την αξιοπρέπεια και την ελεύθερη ανάπτυξη της προσωπικότητάς του.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 23

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να εργάζεται και να επιλέγει ελεύθερα το επάγγελμά του, να έχει δίκαιες και ικανοποιητικές συνθήκες δουλειάς και να προστατεύεται από την ανεργία.

2. 'Ολοι, χωρίς καμία διάκριση, έχουν το δικαίωμα ίσης αμοιβής για ίση εργασία.

3. Κάθε εργαζόμενος έχει δικαίωμα δίκαιης και ικανοποιητικής αμοιβής, που να εξασφαλίζει σε αυτόν και την οικογένειά του συνθήκες ζωής άξιες στην ανθρώπινη αξιοπρέπεια. Η αμοιβή της εργασίας, αν υπάρχει, πρέπει να συμπληρώνεται με άλλα μέσα κοινωνικής προστασίας.

4. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να ιδρύει μαζί με άλλους συνδικάτα και να συμμετέχει σε συνδικάτα για την προάσπιση των συμφερόντων του.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 24

Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα στην ανάπαυση, σε ελεύθερο χρόνο, και ιδιαίτερα, σε λογικό περιορισμό του χρόνου εργασίας και σε περιοδικές άδειες με πλήρεις αποδοχές.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 25

1. Καθένας έχει δικαίωμα σε ένα βιοτικό επίπεδο ικανό να εξασφαλίσει στον ίδιο και στην οικογένεια του υγεία και ευημερία, και ειδικότερα τροφή, ρουχισμό, κατοικία, ιατρική περίθαλψη όπως και τις απαραίτητες κοινωνικές υπηρεσίες. 'Εχει ακόμα δικαίωμα σε ασφάλιση για την ανεργία, την αρρώστια, την αναπηρία, τη χηρεία, τη γεροντική ηλικία, όπως και για όλες τις άλλες περιπτώσεις που στερείται τα μέσα της συντήρησής του, εξαιτίας περιστάσεων ανεξαρτήτων της θέλησης του.

2. Η μητρότητα και η παιδική ηλικία έχουν δικαίωμα ειδικής μέριμνας και περίθαλψης. 'Ολα τα παιδιά, ανεξάρτητα αν είναι νόμιμα ή εξώγαμα, απολαμβάνουν την ίδια κοινωνική προστασία.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 26

1. Καθένας έχει δικαίωμα στην εκπαίδευση. Η εκπαίδευση πρέπει να παρέχεται δωρεάν, τουλάχιστον στη στοιχειώδη και βασική βαθμίδα της. Η στοιχειώδης εκπαίδευση είναι υποχρεωτική. Η τεχνική και επαγγελματική εκπαίδευση πρέπει να εξασφαλίζεται για όλους. Η πρόσβαση στην ανώτατη παιδεία πρέπει να είναι ανοικτή σε όλους, υπό ίσους όρους, ανάλογα με τις ικανότητες τους.

2. Η εκπαίδευση πρέπει να αποβλέπει στην πλήρη ανάπτυξη της ανθρώπινης προσωπικότητας και στην ενίσχυση του σεβασμού των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων και των θεμελιακών ελευθεριών. Πρέπει να προάγει την κατανόηση, την ανεκτικότητα και τη φιλία ανάμεσα σε όλα τα έθνη και σε όλες τις φυλές και τις θρησκευτικές ομάδες, και να ευνοεί την ανάπτυξη των δραστηριοτήτων των Ηνωμένων Εθνών για τη διατήρηση της ειρήνης.

3. Οι γονείς έχουν, κατά προτεραιότητα, το δικαίωμα να επιλέγουν το είδος της παιδείας που θα δοθεί στα παιδιά τους.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 27

1. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να συμμετέχει ελεύθερα στην πνευματική ζωή της κοινότητας, να χαίρεται τις καλές τέχνες και να μετέχει στην επιστημονική πρόοδο και στα αγαθά της.

2. Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να προστατεύονται τα ηθικά και υλικά συμφέροντά του που απορρέουν από κάθε είδους επιστημονική, λογοτεχνική ή καλλιτεχνική παραγωγή του.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 28

Καθένας έχει το δικαίωμα να επικρατεί μια κοινωνική και διεθνής τάξη, μέσα στην οποία τα δικαιώματα και οι ελευθερίες που προκηρύσσει η παρούσα Διακήρυξη να μπορούν να πραγματώνονται σε όλη τους την έκταση.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 29

1. Το άτομο έχει καθήκοντα απέναντι στην κοινότητα, μέσα στα πλαίσια της οποίας και μόνο είναι δυνατή η ελεύθερη και ολοκληρωμένη ανάπτυξη της προσωπικότητάς του.

2. Στην άσκηση των δικαιωμάτων του και στην απόλαυση των ελευθεριών του κανείς δεν υπόκειται παρά μόνο στους περιορισμούς που ορίζονται από τους νόμους, με αποκλειστικό σκοπό να εξασφαλίζεται η αναγνώριση και ο σεβασμός των δικαιωμάτων και των ελευθεριών των άλλων, και να ικανοποιούνται οι δίκαιες απαιτήσεις της ηθικής, της δημόσιας τάξης και του γενικού καλού, σε μια δημοκρατική κοινωνία.

3. Τα δικαιώματα αυτά και οι ελευθερίες δεν μπορούν, σε καμία περίπτωση, να ασκούνται αντίθετα προς τους σκοπούς και τις αρχές των Ηνωμένων Εθνών.

ΑΡΘΡΟ 30

Καμιά διάταξη της παρούσας Διακήρυξης δεν μπορεί να ερμηνευθεί ότι παρέχει σε ένα κράτος, σε μια ομάδα ή σε ένα άτομο οποιοδήποτε δικαίωμα να επιδίδεται σε ενέργειες ή να εκτελεί πράξεις που αποβλέπουν στην άρνηση των δικαιωμάτων και των ελευθεριών που εξαγγέλλονται σε αυτήν.

Déclaration universelle des droits de l’homme

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - French

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

Préambule

Considérant que la reconnaissance de la dignité inhérente à tous les membres de la famille humaine et de leurs droits égaux et inaliénables constitue le fondement de la liberté, de la justice et de la paix dans le monde,

Considérant que la méconnaissance et le mépris des droits de l’homme ont conduit à des actes de barbarie qui révoltent la conscience de l’humanité et que l’avènement d’un monde où les êtres humains seront libres de parler et de croire, libérés de la terreur et de la misère, a été proclamé comme la plus haute aspiration de l’homme,

Considérant qu’il est essentiel que les droits de l’homme soient protégés par un régime de droit pour que l’homme ne soit pas contraint, en suprême recours, à la révolte contre la tyrannie et l’oppression,

Considérant qu’il est essentiel d’encourager le développement de relations amicales entre nations,

Considérant que dans la Charte les peuples des Nations Unies ont proclamé à nouveau leur foi dans les droits fondamentaux de l’homme, dans la dignité et la valeur de la personne humaine, dans l’égalité des droits des hommes et des femmes, et qu’ils se sont déclarés résolus à favoriser le progrès social et à instaurer de meilleures conditions de vie dans une liberté plus grande,

Considérant que les États Membres se sont engagés à assurer, en coopération avec l’Organisation des Nations Unies, le respect universel et effectif des droits de l’homme et des libertés fondamentales,

Considérant qu’une conception commune de ces droits et libertés est de la plus haute importance pour remplir pleinement cet engagement,

L’Assemblée générale

Proclame la présente Déclaration universelle des droits de l’homme comme l’idéal commun à atteindre par tous les peuples et toutes les nations afin que tous les individus et tous les organes de la société, ayant cette Déclaration constamment à l’esprit, s’efforcent, par l’enseignement et l’éducation, de développer le respect de ces droits et libertés et d’en assurer, par des mesures progressives d’ordre national et international, la reconnaissance et l’application universelles et effectives, tant parmi les populations des États Membres eux‐mêmes que parmi celles des territoires placés sous leur juridiction.

Article premier

Tous les êtres humains naissent libres et égaux en dignité et en droits. Ils sont doués de raison et de conscience et doivent agir les uns envers les autres dans un esprit de fraternité.

Article 2

Chacun peut se prévaloir de tous les droits et de toutes les libertés proclamés dans la présente Déclaration, sans distinction aucune, notamment de race, de couleur, de sexe, de langue, de religion, d’opinion politique ou de toute autre opinion, d’origine nationale ou sociale, de fortune, de naissance ou de toute autre situation.

De plus, il ne sera fait aucune distinction fondée sur le statut politique, juridique ou international du pays ou du territoire dont une personne est ressortissante, que ce pays ou territoire soit indépendant, sous tutelle, non autonome ou soumis à une limitation quelconque de souveraineté.

Article 3

Tout individu a droit à la vie, à la liberté et à la sûreté de sa personne.

Article 4

Nul ne sera tenu en esclavage ni en servitude ; l’esclavage et la traite des esclaves sont interdits sous toutes leurs formes.

Article 5

Nul ne sera soumis à la torture, ni à des peines ou traitements cruels, inhumains ou dégradants.

Article 6

Chacun a le droit à la reconnaissance en tous lieux de sa personnalité juridique.

Article 7

Tous sont égaux devant la loi et ont droit sans distinction à une égale protection de la loi. Tous ont droit à une protection égale contre toute discrimination qui violerait la présente Déclaration et contre toute provocation à une telle discrimination.

Article 8

Toute personne a droit à un recours effectif devant les juridictions nationales compétentes contre les actes violant les droits fondamentaux qui lui sont reconnus par la constitution ou par la loi.

Article 9

Nul ne peut être arbitrairement arrêté, détenu ni exilé.

Article 10

Toute personne a droit, en pleine égalité, à ce que sa cause soit entendue équitablement et publiquement par un tribunal indépendant et impartial, qui décidera, soit de ses droits et obligations, soit du bien fondé de toute accusation en matière pénale dirigée contre elle.

Article 11

1. Toute personne accusée d’un acte délictueux est présumée innocente jusqu’à ce que sa culpabilité ait été légalement établie au cours d’un procès public où toutes les garanties nécessaires à sa défense lui auront été assurées.

2. Nul ne sera condamné pour des actions ou omissions qui, au moment où elles ont été commises, ne constituaient pas un acte délictueux d’après le droit national ou international. De même, il ne sera infligé aucune peine plus forte que celle qui était applicable au moment où l’acte délictueux a été commis.

Article 12

Nul ne sera l’objet d’immixtions arbitraires dans sa vie privée, sa famille, son domicile ou sa correspondance, ni d’atteintes à son honneur et à sa réputation. Toute personne a droit à la protection de la loi contre de telles immixtions ou de telles atteintes.

Article 13

1. Toute personne a le droit de circuler librement et de choisir sa résidence à l’intérieur d’un État.

2. Toute personne a le droit de quitter tout pays, y compris le sien, et de revenir dans son pays.

Article 14

1. Devant la persécution, toute personne a le droit de chercher asile et de bénéficier de l’asile en d’autres pays.

2. Ce droit ne peut être invoqué dans le cas de poursuites réellement fondées sur un crime de droit commun ou sur des agissements contraires aux buts et aux principes des Nations Unies.

Article 15

1. Tout individu a droit à une nationalité.

2. Nul ne peut être arbitrairement privé de sa nationalité, ni du droit de changer de nationalité.

Article 16

1. A partir de l’âge nubile, l’homme et la femme, sans aucune restriction quant à la race, la nationalité ou la religion, ont le droit de se marier et de fonder une famille. Ils ont des droits égaux au regard du mariage, durant le mariage et lors de sa dissolution.

2. Le mariage ne peut être conclu qu’avec le libre et plein consentement des futurs époux.

3. La famille est l’élément naturel et fondamental de la société et a droit à la protection de la société et de l’État.

Article 17

1. Toute personne, aussi bien seule qu’en collectivité, a droit à la propriété.

2. Nul ne peut être arbitrairement privé de sa propriété.

Article 18

Toute personne a droit à la liberté de pensée, de conscience et de religion ; ce droit implique la liberté de changer de religion ou de conviction ainsi que la liberté de manifester sa religion ou sa conviction, seule ou en commun, tant en public qu’en privé, par l’enseignement, les pratiques, le culte et l’accomplissement des rites.

Article 19

Tout individu a droit à la liberté d’opinion et d’expression, ce qui implique le droit de ne pas être inquiété pour ses opinions et celui de chercher, de recevoir et de répandre, sans considérations de frontières, les informations et les idées par quelque moyen d’expression que ce soit.

Article 20

1. Toute personne a droit à la liberté de réunion et d’association pacifiques.

2. Nul ne peut être obligé de faire partie d’une association.

Article 21

1. Toute personne a le droit de prendre part à la direction des affaires publiques de son pays, soit directement, soit par l’intermédiaire de représentants librement choisis.

2. Toute personne a droit à accéder, dans des conditions d’égalité, aux fonctions publiques de son pays.

3. La volonté du peuple est le fondement de l’autorité des pouvoirs publics ; cette volonté doit s’exprimer par des élections honnêtes qui doivent avoir lieu périodiquement, au suffrage universel égal et au vote secret ou suivant une procédure équivalente assurant la liberté du vote.

Article 22

Toute personne, en tant que membre de la société, a droit à la sécurité sociale ; elle est fondée à obtenir la satisfaction des droits économiques, sociaux et culturels indispensables à sa dignité et au libre développement de sa personnalité, grâce à l’effort national et à la coopération internationale, compte tenu de l’organisation et des ressources de chaque pays.

Article 23

1. Toute personne a droit au travail, au libre choix de son travail, à des conditions équitables et satisfaisantes de travail et à la protection contre le chômage.

2. Tous ont droit, sans aucune discrimination, à un salaire égal pour un travail égal.

3. Quiconque travaille a droit à une rémunération équitable et satisfaisante lui assurant ainsi qu’à sa famille une existence conforme à la dignité humaine et complétée, s’il y a lieu, par tous autres moyens de protection sociale.

4. Toute personne a le droit de fonder avec d’autres des syndicats et de s’affilier à des syndicats pour la défense de ses intérêts.

Article 24

Toute personne a droit au repos et aux loisirs et notamment à une limitation raisonnable de la durée du travail et à des congés payés périodiques.

Article 25

1. Toute personne a droit à un niveau de vie suffisant pour assurer sa santé, son bien‐être et ceux de sa famille, notamment pour l’alimentation, l’habillement, le logement, les soins médicaux ainsi que pour les services sociaux nécessaires ; elle a droit à la sécurité en cas de chômage, de maladie, d’invalidité, de veuvage, de vieillesse ou dans les autres cas de perte de ses moyens de subsistance par suite de circonstances indépendantes de sa volonté.

2. La maternité et l’enfance ont droit à une aide et à une assistance spéciales. Tous les enfants, qu’ils soient nés dans le mariage ou hors mariage, jouissent de la même protection sociale.

Article 26

1. Toute personne a droit à l’éducation. L’éducation doit être gratuite, au moins en ce qui concerne l’enseignement élémentaire et fondamental. L’enseignement élémentaire est obligatoire. L’enseignement technique et professionnel doit être généralisé ; l’accès aux études supérieures doit être ouvert en pleine égalité à tous en fonction de leur mérite.

2. L’éducation doit viser au plein épanouissement de la personnalité humaine et au renforcement du respect des droits de l’homme et des libertés fondamentales. Elle doit favoriser la compréhension, la tolérance et l’amitié entre toutes les nations et tous les groupes raciaux ou religieux, ainsi que le développement des activités des Nations Unies pour le maintien de la paix.

3. Les parents ont, par priorité, le droit de choisir le genre d’éducation à donner à leurs enfants.

Article 27

1. Toute personne a le droit de prendre part librement à la vie culturelle de la communauté, de jouir des arts et de participer au progrès scientifique et aux bienfaits qui en résultent.

2. Chacun a droit à la protection des intérêts moraux et matériels découlant de toute production scientifique, littéraire ou artistique dont il est l’auteur.

Article 28

Toute personne a droit à ce que règne, sur le plan social et sur le plan international, un ordre tel que les droits et libertés énoncés dans la présente Déclaration puissent y trouver plein effet.

Article 29

1. L’individu a des devoirs envers la communauté dans laquelle seul le libre et plein développement de sa personnalité est possible.

2. Dans l’exercice de ses droits et dans la jouissance de ses libertés, chacun n’est soumis qu’aux limitations établies par la loi exclusivement en vue d’assurer la reconnaissance et le respect des droits et libertés d’autrui et afin de satisfaire aux justes exigences de la morale, de l’ordre public et du bien‐être général dans une société démocratique.

3. Ces droits et libertés ne pourront, en aucun cas, s’exercer contrairement aux buts et aux principes des Nations Unies.

Article 30

Aucune disposition de la présente Déclaration ne peut être interprétée comme impliquant pour un État, un groupement ou un individu un droit quelconque de se livrer à une activité ou d’accomplir un acte visant à la destruction des droits et libertés qui y sont énoncés.

Declaração dos Direitos Humanos

Universal Declaration of Human Rights - Portuguese (Brazil)

© 1996 – 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights

This HTML version prepared by the UDHR in Unicode project.

A Declaração Universal dos Direitos Humanos é um dos documentos básicos das Nações Unidas e foi assinada em 1948. Nela, são enumerados os direitos que todos os seres humanos possuem.

Preâmbulo

Considerando que o reconhecimento da dignidade inerente a todos os membros da família humana e de seus direitos iguais e inalienáveis é o fundamento da liberdade, da justiça e da paz no mundo,

Considerando que o desprezo e o desrespeito pelos direitos humanos resultaram em atos bárbaros que ultrajaram a consciência da Humanidade e que o advento de um mundo em que os todos gozem de liberdade de palavra, de crença e da liberdade de viverem a salvo do temor e da necessidade foi proclamado como a mais alta aspiração do ser humano comum,

Considerando ser essencial que os direitos humanos sejam protegidos pelo império da lei, para que o ser humano não seja compelido, como último recurso, à rebelião contra a tirania e a opressão,

Considerando ser essencial promover o desenvolvimento de relações amistosas entre as nações,

Considerando que os povos das Nações Unidas reafirmaram, na Carta da ONU, sua fé nos direitos humanos fundamentais, na dignidade e no valor do ser humano e na igualdade de direitos entre homens e mulheres, e que decidiram promover o progresso social e melhores condições de vida em uma liberdade mais ampla,

Considerando que os Estados‐Membros se comprometeram a promover, em cooperação com as Nações Unidas, o respeito universal aos direitos e liberdades humanas fundamentais e a observância desses direitos e liberdades,

Considerando que uma compreensão comum desses direitos e liberdades é da mais alta importância para o pleno cumprimento desse compromisso,

agora portanto,

A Assembléia Geral proclama a presente Declaração Universal dos Direitos Humanos

como o ideal comum a ser atingido por todos os povos e todas as nações, com o objetivo de que cada indivíduo e cada órgão da sociedade, tendo sempre em mente esta Declaração, se esforce, através do ensino e da educação, por promover o respeito a esses direitos e liberdades, e, pela adoção de medidas progressivas de caráter nacional e internacional, por assegurar o seu reconhecimento e a sua observância universal e efetiva, tanto entre os povos dos próprios Estados‐Membros, quanto entre os povos dos territórios sob sua jurisdição.

Artigo I.

Todos os seres humanos nascem livres e iguais em dignidade e direitos. São dotados de razão e consciência e devem agir em relação uns aos outros com espírito de fraternidade.

Artigo II.

Todo ser humano tem capacidade para gozar os direitos e as liberdades estabelecidos nesta Declaração, sem distinção de qualquer espécie, seja de raça, cor, sexo, idioma, religião, opinião política ou de outra natureza, origem nacional ou social, riqueza, nascimento, ou qualquer outra condição.

Não será também feita nenhuma distinção fundada na condição política, jurídica ou internacional do país ou território a que pertença uma pessoa, quer se trate de um território independente, sob tutela, sem governo próprio, quer sujeito a qualquer outra limitação de soberania.

Artigo III.

Todo ser humano tem direito à vida, à liberdade e à segurança pessoal.

Artigo IV.

Ninguém será mantido em escravidão ou servidão; a escravidão e o tráfico de escravos serão proibidos em todas as suas formas.

Artigo V.

Ninguém será submetido à tortura nem a tratamento ou castigo cruel, desumano ou degradante.

Artigo VI.

Todo ser humano tem o direito de ser, em todos os lugares, reconhecido como pessoa perante a lei.

Artigo VII.

Todos são iguais perante a lei e têm direito, sem qualquer distinção, a igual proteção da lei. Todos têm direito a igual proteção contra qualquer discriminação que viole a presente Declaração e contra qualquer incitamento a tal discriminação.

Artigo VIII.

Todo ser humano tem direito a receber dos tribunais nacionais competentes remédio efetivo para os atos que violem os direitos fundamentais que lhe sejam reconhecidos pela constituição ou pela lei.

Artigo IX.

Ninguém será arbitrariamente preso, detido ou exilado.

Artigo X.

Todo ser humano tem direito, em plena igualdade, a uma justa e pública audiência por parte de um tribunal independente e imparcial, para decidir sobre seus direitos e deveres ou do fundamento de qualquer acusação criminal contra ele.

Artigo XI.

1. Todo ser humano acusado de um ato delituoso tem o direito de ser presumido inocente até que a sua culpabilidade tenha sido provada de acordo com a lei, em julgamento público no qual lhe tenham sido asseguradas todas as garantias necessárias à sua defesa.

2. Ninguém poderá ser culpado por qualquer ação ou omissão que, no momento, não constituíam delito perante o direito nacional ou internacional. Também não será imposta pena mais forte do que aquela que, no momento da prática, era aplicável ao ato delituoso.

Artigo XII.

Ninguém será sujeito à interferência em sua vida privada, em sua família, em seu lar ou em sua correspondência, nem a ataque à sua honra e reputação. Todo ser humano tem direito à proteção da lei contra tais interferências ou ataques.

Artigo XIII.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito à liberdade de locomoção e residência dentro das fronteiras de cada Estado.

2. Todo ser humano tem o direito de deixar qualquer país, inclusive o próprio, e a este regressar.

Artigo XIV.

1. Todo ser humano, vítima de perseguição, tem o direito de procurar e de gozar asilo em outros países.

2. Este direito não pode ser invocado em caso de perseguição legitimamente motivada por crimes de direito comum ou por atos contrários aos objetivos e princípios das Nações Unidas.

Artigo XV.

1. Todo homem tem direito a uma nacionalidade.

2. Ninguém será arbitrariamente privado de sua nacionalidade, nem do direito de mudar de nacionalidade.

Artigo XVI.

1. Os homens e mulheres de maior idade, sem qualquer restrição de raça, nacionalidade ou religião, têm o direito de contrair matrimônio e fundar uma família. Gozam de iguais direitos em relação ao casamento, sua duração e sua dissolução.

2. O casamento não será válido senão com o livre e pleno consentimento dos nubentes.

3. A família é o núcleo natural e fundamental da sociedade e tem direito à proteção da sociedade e do Estado.

Artigo XVII.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito à propriedade, só ou em sociedade com outros.

2. Ninguém será arbitrariamente privado de sua propriedade.

Artigo XVIII.

Todo ser humano tem direito à liberdade de pensamento, consciência e religião; este direito inclui a liberdade de mudar de religião ou crença e a liberdade de manifestar essa religião ou crença, pelo ensino, pela prática, pelo culto e pela observância, em público ou em particular.

Artigo XIX.

Todo ser humano tem direito à liberdade de opinião e expressão; este direito inclui a liberdade de, sem interferência, ter opiniões e de procurar, receber e transmitir informações e idéias por quaisquer meios e independentemente de fronteiras.

Artigo XX.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito à liberdade de reunião e associação pacífica.

2. Ninguém pode ser obrigado a fazer parte de uma associação.

Artigo XXI.

1. Todo ser humano tem o direito de fazer parte no governo de seu país diretamente ou por intermédio de representantes livremente escolhidos.

2. Todo ser humano tem igual direito de acesso ao serviço público do seu país.

3. A vontade do povo será a base da autoridade do governo; esta vontade será expressa em eleições periódicas e legítimas, por sufrágio universal, por voto secreto ou processo equivalente que assegure a liberdade de voto.

Artigo XXII.

Todo ser humano, como membro da sociedade, tem direito à segurança social, à realização pelo esforço nacional, pela cooperação internacional e de acordo com a organização e recursos de cada Estado, dos direitos econômicos, sociais e culturais indispensáveis à sua dignidade e ao livre desenvolvimento da sua personalidade.

Artigo XXIII.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito ao trabalho, à livre escolha de emprego, a condições justas e favoráveis de trabalho e à proteção contra o desemprego.

2. Todo ser humano, sem qualquer distinção, tem direito a igual remuneração por igual trabalho.

3. Todo ser humano que trabalha tem direito a uma remuneração justa e satisfatória, que lhe assegure, assim como à sua família, uma existência compatível com a dignidade humana e a que se acrescentarão, se necessário, outros meios de proteção social.

4. Todo ser humano tem direito a organizar sindicatos e a neles ingressar para proteção de seus interesses.

Artigo XXIV.

Todo ser humano tem direito a repouso e lazer, inclusive a limitação razoável das horas de trabalho e a férias remuneradas periódicas.

Artigo XXV.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito a um padrão de vida capaz de assegurar‐lhe, e a sua família, saúde e bem‐estar, inclusive alimentação, vestuário, habitação, cuidados médicos e os serviços sociais indispensáveis, e direito à segurança em caso de desemprego, doença, invalidez, viuvez, velhice ou outros casos de perda dos meios de subsistência em circunstâncias fora de seu controle.

2. A maternidade e a infância têm direito a cuidados e assistência especiais. Todas as crianças, nascidas dentro ou fora do matrimônio gozarão da mesma proteção social.

Artigo XXVI.

1. Todo ser humano tem direito à instrução. A instrução será gratuita, pelo menos nos graus elementares e fundamentais. A instrução elementar será obrigatória. A instrução técnico‐profissional será acessível a todos, bem como a instrução superior, esta baseada no mérito.

2. A instrução será orientada no sentido do pleno desenvolvimento da personalidade humana e do fortalecimento do respeito pelos direitos humanos e pelas liberdades fundamentais. A instrução promoverá a compreensão, a tolerância e a amizade entre todas as nações e grupos raciais ou religiosos, e coadjuvará as atividades das Nações Unidas em prol da manutenção da paz.

3. Os pais têm prioridade de direito na escolha do gênero de instrução que será ministrada a seus filhos.

Artigo XXVII.

1. Todo ser humano tem o direito de participar livremente da vida cultural da comunidade, de fruir das artes e de participar do progresso científico e de seus benefícios.

2. Todo ser humano tem direito à proteção dos interesses morais e materiais decorrentes de qualquer produção científica literária ou artística da qual seja autor.

Artigo XXVIII.

Todo ser humano tem direito a uma ordem social e internacional em que os direitos e liberdades estabelecidos na presente Declaração possam ser plenamente realizados.

Artigo XXIX.

1. Todo ser humano tem deveres para com a comunidade, na qual o livre e pleno desenvolvimento de sua personalidade é possível.

2. No exercício de seus direitos e liberdades, todo ser humano estará sujeito apenas às limitações determinadas pela lei, exclusivamente com o fim de assegurar o devido reconhecimento e respeito dos direitos e liberdades de outrem e de satisfazer as justas exigências da moral, da ordem pública e do bem‐estar de uma sociedade democrática.

3. Esses direitos e liberdades não podem, em hipótese alguma, ser exercidos contrariamente aos objetivos e princípios das Nações Unidas.

Artigo XXX.

Nenhuma disposição da presente Declaração pode ser interpretada como o reconhecimento a qualquer Estado, grupo ou pessoa, do direito de exercer qualquer atividade ou praticar qualquer ato destinado à destruição de quaisquer dos direitos e liberdades aqui estabelecidos.